The final section of chapter one of your text
is a discussion of amyloid.
Amyloid is important to discuss in this particular sequence
because it is another mechanism
by which cells can become injured,
and we've obviously been talking about cellular injury
and cell death, and amyloid is one way
by which cells can become injured and eventually die
because amyloid has the ability to damage tissues.
Now before we can go further,
we actually need to define what amyloid is.
So amyloid is a misfolded protein, that's important,
that deposits in the extracellular space.
That's actually very important as well.
So it is a misfolded protein and it deposits outside of the cell
in the extracellular space,
and it's this deposition in the extracellular space
that eventually results in damage to tissues.
So cells become injured and the tissues become damaged.
The next important principle concerning amyloid is that multiple proteins can deposit as amyloid.
Amyloid is not one protein.
Amyloid is a broad category that refers to multiple proteins depositing in a particular way.
And there are a few common characteristics of amyloid and those are relatively important to be familiar with,
so let's mention them here.
First of all, the misfolded proteins that deposit as amyloid usually have a beta pleated sheet configuration.
That's important.
And number two, and what was the classic teaching and you're perhaps familiar with,
is the fact that the proteins that deposit as amyloid, they pick up a stain called Congo red.
So they'll turn red with this Congo red stain.
And very classically, when placed under polarized light, they reveal an apple green birefringence.
Apple green birefringence.
So here's a couple images to highlight that.
This is a picture of amyloid with a Congo red stain.
Let's figure 1.13 in your text.
And let's just focus here, what I'm boxing in here with this square.
Let's focus here for a minute.
First of all, notice that the center of this area here, the center of this square, sort of represents a blood vessel.
So this circular space in the center represents a blood vessel.
And notice that this dense pink material here, which is surrounding the blood vessel, actually represents amyloid.
And that's what's staining red with the Congo red stain.
Notice that the amyloid is outside of the cells.
It's in the extracellular matrix.
And also notice that it tends to deposit around blood vessels.
And that's going to be very important in another subsequent discussion when we talk about Alzheimer's disease
and the fact that in Alzheimer's disease you get amyloid plaques, but that you also get amyloid around blood vessels.
But generally speaking, it is a principle that amyloid often deposits around blood vessels.
This is the second stain to be familiar with, and that is when the Congo red stain is taken and it's placed under polarized light,
it reveals this apple green birefringence, which is characteristic of amyloid.
Now, amyloid can deposit, amyloid does deposit in tissues, and that deposition can be systemic or localized.
Now what do we mean by systemic?
Systemic means that it deposits in multiple organ systems of the body.
So it's a diffuse deposition, and localized means that it's localized to a particular organ.
Now, in systemic amyloid, we're going to focus on systemic amyloid first.
Systemic amyloid is divided into primary and secondary types, and we're going to highlight those now.
So what is primary amyloidosis?
Primary amyloidosis is when there is systemic deposition of amyloid,
and that systemic deposition of amyloid is a particular protein called AL amyloid.
AL amyloid is derived from immunoglobulin light chain.
So basically, immunoglobulin light chain begins to deposit in various tissues throughout the body.
That's primary amyloidosis.
Alright, let's take a step back.
When you think about light chain, you should basically remember that light chain, or immunoglobulin light chain,
is part of immunoglobulin.
And if I draw you a picture of immunoglobulin, like this and here,
you'll remember that there are heavy chains, as I've drawn,
and that associated with those heavy chains are these two light chains, which are here, these light chains.
Now generally speaking, the plasma cell, when it creates heavy chain and light chain,
it creates it in a balance, so that the amount of heavy chain and the amount of light chain are relatively equal,
and the heavy chain and the light chain will bind together to produce proper immunoglobulin.
However, in a subset of diseases called plasma cell dyscrasias,
plasma cell dyscrasias is a general term that refers to abnormalities of the plasma cell.
When there are plasma cell dyscrasias, there can be overproduction of the light chain,
and the overproduced light chain will leak out into the blood,
and the light chain can then become misfolded,
and can eventually deposit within tissues, creating a primary amyloidosis.
So that's the characteristic of primary amyloidosis.
And the most important thing, it's derived from immunoglobulin light chain,
it's called AL amyloid, derived from immunoglobulin light chain,
and it's associated with plasma cell dyscrasias.
Secondary amyloidosis refers to systemic deposition of an amyloid called AA amyloid.
And this AA amyloid is actually derived from a protein called SAA.
Now, let's go back and remind ourselves that SAA, the protein SAA,
is actually an acute phase reactant.
So that any time there's inflammation, there's an increase in SAA,
and the SAA can be converted to AA amyloid,
and the AA amyloid can deposit within tissues, creating amyloidosis.
Now, if SAA is an acute phase reactant, then we can derive from that
that secondary amyloidosis is going to be related to circumstances
where there is chronic inflammation.
So for example, if the patient has a chronic inflammatory state,
that can result in secondary amyloidosis.
So what would be some examples of chronic inflammatory states?
Autoimmune diseases like lupus, rheumatoid arthritis, etc.
Another example of a chronic inflammatory state, Crohn's disease.
An example of a chronic inflammatory state, ulcerative colitis.
Another example of chronic inflammatory state, chronic osteomyelitis,
in which you get a long progressive infection within the bone marrow.
So these are all examples where there's chronic inflammation.
Chronic inflammation results in an increase in SAA.
SAA can become AA, and the AA can deposit as amyloid.
Another circumstance in which we might see secondary amyloidosis is malignancy.
And the idea here is that malignancy, on occasion, can result in a chronic inflammatory state.
And a low-grade chronic inflammatory state because we can have an inflammatory reaction against the tumors,
against the tumor cells.
And so malignancy is associated with secondary amyloidosis.
The third example, which is super rare and likely not to be seen clinically,
except on a very rare occasion, however very commonly shows up on board exams,
is familial Mediterranean fever.
Now, what is familial Mediterranean fever?
Familial Mediterranean fever is actually a dysfunction of the neutrophils.
It is a familial genetically derived dysfunction, which is actually autosomal recessive.
And it occurs in persons of Mediterranean origin.
Now, what's the key consequence of familial Mediterranean fever?
Well, the neutrophils are not functioning properly,
and they can become activated and actually create an attack of acute inflammation.
And that attack of acute inflammation is not really driven by infection,
but instead is sort of this dysfunction of the neutrophils.
And it classically presents with fever, which is what you would expect with inflammation.
So it classically presents with fever.
It also will usually involve serosal surfaces.
And so if it's going to involve serosal surfaces, we'll get some very classic findings.
For example, if it involves a serosal surface of the heart, that's the pericardium,
it can present mimicking myocardial infarction.
If it involves the serosal surface of the abdomen, it can present mimicking acute appendicitis.
And so these are some circumstances, these are some of the classic clinical symptoms of familial Mediterranean fever.
Now, what's important for this particular discussion is that when a patient has an attack,
there's going to be a lot of inflammation.
And a byproduct of that high inflammation will be production of acute phase reactants.
And one of those acute phase reactants is SAA.
And so if SAA is produced during an attack, that can deposit as AA,
which would then obviously be AA amyloid, which can then result in amyloidosis, secondary amyloidosis.
Now, what are the classic clinical findings?
Essentially what you should be aware of is that amyloid can really deposit in multiple tissues throughout the body.
However, there are some classic clinical findings, and that's what I want to emphasize here.
First, the kidney is the most commonly involved organ, high yield.
The kidney is the most commonly involved organ.
And when it is involved, it usually creates nephrotic syndrome, or usually results in nephrotic syndrome.
That's high yield as well.
Nephrotic syndrome we will cover in much more detail when we have renal lectures,
but basically it's a syndrome in which there is a large loss of protein,
classically greater than 3.5 grams over a 24-hour period in the urine.
Another region of the body that can be affected by amyloidosis or is classically affected by amyloidosis is the heart.
And in the heart, we get a restrictive cardiomyopathy.
What's a restrictive cardiomyopathy?
It's a cardiomyopathy or a disease of the heart in which we can't fill the heart properly because the wall of the heart becomes less compliant or less bendable due to the filling of the wall of the heart with amyloid.
And therefore, if we can't fill the heart well, we're not going to be able to pump well.
If we can't pump well, we're going to get eventual heart failure.
Another complication would be arrhythmia.
And then finally, other organs can be involved.
For example, the tongue will become enlarged or can become enlarged.
The bowel can become thickened.
The wall of the bowel can become thickened, leading to malabsorption.
And the liver and the spleen often are enlarged as well.
The diagnosis of amyloidosis requires a tissue biopsy.
It's not a blood test.
It requires you to actually see the amyloid within the tissue and, of course, perform a Congo red stain that shows apple green birefringens.
Targets that are relatively easily accessible include the abdominal fat pad.
So basically, it's a very simple procedure.
A needle is just placed through the abdominal wall into the fat pad and then aspirated.
And the cells are placed on a slide and amyloid would be visible in that way.
The rectum is also a relatively easy target for biopsy.
And the amyloid could be seen in the mucosa of the rectum as well.
The damaged organs in systemic amyloidosis must be transplanted.
If you get end-stage damage, amyloid cannot be removed.
And so that's an important clinical principle concerning amyloidosis.
Now, that was the discussion of systemic amyloidosis.
And now I want to talk about localized amyloidosis.
And in the discussion of localized amyloidosis, the first point here is that the word localized basically refers to the fact that the amyloid deposition is localized to a single organ, usually a single organ or a single tissue in the body.
The first and classic example of localized amyloidosis is senile cardiac amyloidosis.
So the name kind of gives it away.
Senile, usually seen in the elderly.
Cardiac, usually involves the heart alone.
And of course, amyloidosis means that there's an amyloid depositing there.
It is important for examination purposes to know what the amyloid is in this particular circumstance.
It is non-mutated serum transthyretin.
So we could just basically say this.
It is serum transthyretin.
And you'll see why I'm highlighting the non-mutated part in a moment.
So serum transthyretin is the second most common protein within the blood.
And this protein, over very long periods of time, can eventually deposit, particularly in the heart, resulting in senile cardiac amyloidosis.
This would be asymptomatic.
That's important.
And it would be seen in the elderly.
In fact, it's relatively common, present in about 25% of individuals over the age of 80.
Another localized amyloidosis, which is sort of in contrast to senile cardiac amyloidosis, is familial amyloid cardiomyopathy.
Now, in this particular case, it's serum transthyretin that deposits.
However, it is a mutated, not a normal, but a mutated serum transthyretin that deposits in the heart.
This also results in disease.
Remember that in senile cardiac amyloidosis, it was asymptomatic.
But here, this leads to a restrictive cardiomyopathy.
Again, restrictive cardiomyopathy implying that the wall of the heart gets full of amyloid.
Because it's full of amyloid, it's not able to expand.
It becomes less compliant, and therefore it can't fill.
So it's restricted from filling.
And therefore, as a consequence of that, it can't pump properly.
And if it can't pump properly, eventually the patient goes into cardiac failure.
This is a familial circumstance.
5% of African Americans actually carry the mutated gene.
So those are the key highlights for familial amyloid cardiomyopathy.
The next of the examples of localized amyloidosis is type 2 diabetes.
In type 2 diabetes, recall that the problem is a resistance to insulin at the level of the skeletal muscle and the adipose tissue.
And that resistance to insulin initially results in the pancreas actually putting out excess insulin until eventually the pancreas burns out.
And so, a consequence of the production of that excess insulin is actually the production of a byproduct of insulin, which is called amylin.
And amylin deposits in the islets of the pancreas.
So the classic histologic finding in type 2 diabetes is deposition of amyloid within the islets of the pancreas.
And that amyloid is called amylin, which is again derived from insulin.
Another example, Alzheimer's disease.
In Alzheimer's disease, there is deposition of amyloid within the brain as plaques.
Those plaques are actually made up of an amyloid called A-beta amyloid.
It's important to know A-beta amyloid.
A-beta amyloid is derived from a protein called the beta amyloid precursor protein.
Beta amyloid precursor protein.
So, in Alzheimer's disease, we see amyloid plaques.
The amyloid plaques contain A-beta amyloid.
And the A-beta amyloid is actually derived from beta amyloid precursor protein.
Important to know and relatively high yield is that the beta amyloid precursor protein,
the gene that produces that protein, is on chromosome 21.
Why is that important?
It's important because it ties into a very important clinical high yield association.
And that is that most individuals with Down syndrome, i.e. individuals who have three copies of chromosome 21,
actually develop Alzheimer's disease by the age of 40.
And that's an example of early onset Alzheimer's disease.
By early onset, what we mean is that the patient gets Alzheimer's disease at an age earlier than would normally be expected.
An additional type of localized amyloidosis is dialysis-associated amyloidosis.
A few very high yield principles here.
Number one, the amyloid that deposits is called beta-2 microglobulin.
Number two, it deposits in joints.
And number three, it occurs in patients who are on dialysis.
So, let's take a step back and just review one quick principle.
And that is, what is beta-2 microglobulin?
So, recall that one of the surface molecules present on all nucleated cells and platelets is MHC class I.
An MHC class I has a transmembrane domain and an extracellular domain.
An important molecule that provides structural support for MHC class I is called beta-2 microglobulin.
So, beta-2 microglobulin.
Without beta-2 microglobulin, MHC class I is not well expressed on the surface of cells.
Now, patients who get kidney failure and have to go on dialysis.
When they go on dialysis, the beta-2 microglobulin is not filtered well from the blood.
And so, because it's not filtered well, it builds up in the blood.
And as it builds up in the blood, it can deposit in joints.
And these are the classic high yields of this particular entity.
Again, it's dialysis associated.
The deposition is beta-2 microglobulin.
Beta-2 microglobulin is a component, a structural component, of MHC class I.
And this beta-2 microglobulin will deposit in joints as a localized amyloidosis.
And the final localized amyloidosis arises in medullary carcinoma of the thyroid.
Recall that medullary carcinoma of the thyroid is a tumor of the thyroid,
and that tumor is a tumor that's derived from C cells.
And C cells are neuroendocrine-derived cells present within the thyroid
that actually produce a protein called calcitonin.
Now, if there is a tumor of C cells, then there is overproduction of calcitonin,
and part of that excess calcitonin can deposit within the tumor,
creating amyloid in association with medullary carcinoma of the thyroid.
And the classic histologic description is that there are tumor cells in an amyloid background.
And this can show up on examinations where they tell you that a patient has a thyroid mask,
a fine needle aspiration is performed, i.e., a needle is stuck into the thyroid and cells are pulled away.
That's the way by which we biopsy the thyroid.
By the way, that's an important principle, i.e., that the thyroid is biopsied by fine needle aspiration.
So the needle is placed in the tumor, the cells are pulled away,
and they tell you that the pathologist sees tumor cells in an amyloid background.
That tells you that you're dealing with medullary carcinoma, especially on an examination.
And that really is the last of the localized amyloidosis, and that is the last of chapter 1.
End of chapter 1